Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 12 -- Letters from Franklin 1733-1789 Mss.B.F85inventory12
American Philosophical Society
- Letters from Benjamin Franklin
  - to The Speaker and Comm[ittee of the Pennsylvania Assembly]., 1758 June 10; A. Dr. of L. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    The case of [William] Moore and [William] Smith. Mr. [Robert] Charles attempted to ascertain how far our privileges would be affected by coming immediately under the Crown; recommends that we remove the prejudices that have spread in England against them. The Proprietors are determined to discard their present Governor as soon as they find a successor.
    (Conclusion missing.)
    Printed in Works (Bigelow, III, 19; Smyth, III, 443).
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin, Philadelphia., 1758 September 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Will send her some stuff for chair bottoms, and an iron oven if he can get it on board. Has a violent cold. Billy [Franklin] still in the country. They have lately met with a small rebuff in France. The troops are returned.
  - to Mrs. Deborah Franklin., 1758?; A.L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Several particulars about himself. Lodges in Craven street; has four rooms, furnished; living in London very expensive; Billy [his son] is with him and very serviceable; Peter [the servant he took with him] has behaved well. Goodeys he now and then gets a few, but apples seldom. Mrs. [Margaret] Stevenson sends her a pair of knitted [garters]. Will purchase various articles with the £100 she sent him and then send them to her. Will not go to Holland, but intends to see a great part of England as soon as the weather permits travelling. Sends her his picture in miniature.
  - to Mrs. Franklin at Philadelphia, B. Free Franklin, Franklin, Benjamin
    Address Leaf
  - to Mrs. Franklin at Philadelphia via N. York P[e]r Packet, B. Free Franklin, Franklin, Benjamin
  - to Mrs. Deborah Franklin, 1758; A.L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Wrote to Mr. [David] Hall that he received his bills. Hopes his anger is over. Thinks it would improve cousin Josey if he was to come to England and work in some of the best marble shops for a year or two. Is sorry to hear of any disturbance in the Academy the rather as by his introducing that imprudent man [William Smith ?], he thinks he is in some degree the cause of those misfortunes.
  - to [Benjamin] Wilson., 1759 January 28; A. Dr. of L. 8p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Philosophical hints.
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin, Philadelphia., 1759 April 12; A.L.S. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Asks her to tell Mr. [Charles] Thomson that he has just heard that the Proprietor is writing an answer to his book, 1 and will pay off him and the Quakers. Sends her two boxes in which are articles for herself and his friends.
    1 An Enquiry into the Causes of the Alienation of the Delware and Shawaneese Indians, etc.
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin., 1759 August 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Reasons why she does not receive a letter by every pacquet. Sent her some boxes per Capt. Smith but they were not put on the bill of lading. Asks her, in directing his letters, not to put the title, Honorable, before his name.
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin, Philadelphia., 1759 August 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Liverpool
    Has been out on his journey almost three weeks; spent some time at Derbyshire and Manchester; shall set out for Lancaster. The journey agrees very well with him. Not certain whether he is to continue on his route to Scotland or return to London through Yorkshire and Lincolnshire, expects letters at Lancaster that will determine him. Will endeavor to return to Philadelphia early next spring.
  - to The Printer of the [London] Chronicle., [1759.]; A.L.S. "N." 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Manner in which the fresh supply of twelve million pounds, to continue the war, may be most easily borne by the British public.
  - to [John] Hughes. London., 1760 January 7; A. Dr. of L.S. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Prospect of peace. Combants the notion that Canda should be given up; the poor condition of the laws which are sent to England for the King's approbation. Would be glad to render any service to Maryland's Assembly; will take every opportunity of vindicating them.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VII, 192; Bigelow, III, 42; Smyth, IV, 7).
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin, Philadelphia., 1760 February 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Has lately been indisposed with an epidemical cold in the head; took Dr. [John] Fothergill's advice and parted with eight ounces of blood from the back of his head; feels better. Acknowledges the receipt of the apples. Sends her two saucepans, plated silver inside. Was blooded on Sunday, 16 ounces being drawn from him.
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin, Philadelphia., 1760 February 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Recovered from his late indisposition. Bought three saucepans plated silver inside, sent her two of them and kept the smallest in which to make his watergruel. The wine is excellent and the apples are a great comfort to him. Sends Sally [Franklin] a cask of Sheffield goods instead of stationery.
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin, Philadelphia., 1760 March 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Mr. [William] Strahan recommends him to settle in England.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VII, 194; Bigelow, III, 44; Smyth, IV, 9).
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin, Philadelphia., 1760 March 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Is recovered of a slight illness he had, the same that affected him when he returned from Gnadenbut—a pain and giddiness in his head; has been cupped, blooded, physicked, and blistered; became somewhat thin on account of those operations; purposes taking a little journey for a few days during the Easter holidays.
  - to Messrs. Hillary and Scot., 1760 April 8; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Received the invoice and bill for earthenware; desires them to get insurance for £50 which would include the Bale from Kendal; requests them to draw on him for the whole, also asks them to send a copy of the invoice with the goods to Peter Franklin, of Rhode Island if the ship is not gone.
  - to [Cadwallader] Colden., 1760 April 8; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Has ordered to his care from Liverpool 9 casks and I bale which he requests him to forward to Peter Franklin in New Port, Rhode Island. Requests him to pay the freight and charge to him. Hopes to see him during the summer.
  - to --------- --------., 1760 April 8; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Sorry that he cannot be certain as to the time of going into Derbyshire; the Province affairs are to have a hearing before the Board of Trade; he is engaged in public business relating to the Colonies, which will have several hearings before the Lords of Trade and the Council, the first of which is fixed for the 18th and the rest, uncertain, it is imposible for him to forsee when he shall be at liberty; when that time comes, hopes to visit him.
  - to [Deborah Franklin], 1760 June 27; A.L.S. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Previously misidenified as being written to Mary Stevenson. (Corrected May 2013.)
    Advises her not to be troubled by idle reports concerning him. Negro School established by Dr. Bray's Associates. Faults of servants. Marriage in London. Death of David Edwards.
    (A. copy.)
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VII, 201; Bigelow, III, 59; Smyth, IV, 22).
  - to [Mrs. Deborah Franklin]., 1760 August 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Is well. Sends her the eider-down coverlid and bag for the feet, also a camlet for his sister. Peter is concerned that she should be so perplexed about a house.
  - to Isaac Norris, Esq., Speaker., 1760 November 19; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Has received the money from the exchequer and lodged it in the Bank; thinks the money should be laid out in Stocks.
    P.S. The sum lodged in the bank belonging to the Province is £26,648 4s. 6d.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, IV, 86.)
  - to [Isaac] Norris., 1760 November 22; 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    The proportionment of the Parliamentary Grant according to the number of effective men each Colony had in the field, and the amount allotted to the Province of Pennsylvania and the lower counties.
  - to Isaac Norris., [1760.] December; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Relative to stock he purchased for him. Cause for the present lowness of the stocks.
    (A copy.)
  - to ----- -----., [1760.]; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    When he read the "Letter of Two Great Men," the "Remarks" on that Letter, and the "Interest of Great Britian considered with Regard to her Colonies," in answer to those "Remarks," he sat down satisfied that he understood something of the subject, until a sensible writer from Bath perplexed him with assurances that the doctrines of that piece are big with mischief, tending to entertain eternal war upon them, and the reasoning is very fallacious.
  - to A Question in Mercantile Equity., [1760.]; A. Dr. of Mem. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - toThe Printer of the London Chronicle., [1760 ?]; A. Dr. of L.S. "A Briton." 6p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    "Of the Meanes of Disposing the Enemie to Peace." Purporting to be a chapter from an old book of Discourses addressed to some King of Spain.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VII, 217; Bigelow, III, 132; Smyth, IV, 90).
  - to [Mrs. Deborah Franklin]., 1760; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Probable cause for her not receiving his letters. The trouble between Mr. Flower and his wife. Acquaints her that their business draws near a conclusion and that they will have a hearing in less than a month, after which he will be able to fix some day for his return.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VII, 214; Bigelow, III, 130; Smyth, IV, 88).
  - [The interest of Great Britain Considered with Regard to her Colonies and the Acquisitions of Canada and Guadaloupe.], A. Dr. of Diss. 6p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    (InComplete.)
  - The Impeachment of the Earl of Clarendon., [1760.]; A. mem. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    For introducing an arbitrary government into His Majesty's foreign Plantations.
  - to ----- -----., [1760.]; A. Dr. of Diss. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Criticism of the conduct of the Colonial Governor.
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin, Philadelphia., 1761 March 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Is well; sends her a box in which are letters for herself and his friends, also sends two books, which he begs her to deliver to Mr. Coleman.
  - to [John Balfovet], 1761 April 2; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    As Messrs. Portis paid him two bills of the same drawers after a protest, but they refused to do the same with regard to the present bill. Had it been a bill drawn by Mr. [David] Hall he would pay it immediately, but since it is drawn by others, he returns the bill with the protest, that Mr. Hall may recover damages of the drawers.
  - to [Sir John Eardley?] Wilmot., 1761 May 9; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Has received the Act; requests him to call and he will converse with him on the subject.
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin, Philadelphia., 1761 September 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Utrecht, Holland
    Travels in Holland and Flanders; is on his way back to London so as not to miss the Coronation [of George III].
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VII, 229; Bigelow, III, 151; Smyth, IV, 110).
  - to Mr. Ringold, 1761 November 26; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    On his return from a little tour through Flanders and Holland, he found a duplicate of the papers sent him, and among them the address that had been omitted before. Advises that the Address on His Majesty [George III]'s nuptials and congratulation on his accession be blended, and that the other matter be touched in a memorial or petition by itself agreeable to Mr. Wood's advice; which if done, Dr. Franklin is persuaded will be attended with good effect. The Proprietor's and Governor's friends possessed the Ministry with the opinion that the failure of supplies in the Province is due to the Assembly's obstinacy and their disinclination to His Majesty's service. Thanks him for applying to Mr. Green concerning his old account. The retaining of Canada is now become a popular point.
    (Incomplete).
  - to [Mrs. Deborah Franklin]., 1762 March 24; A.L.S. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Death of Mrs. Franklin's mother [Mrs. Read]. Expects to set out for Philadelphia next May. Mr. [William] Strahan is surprised he has not persuaded her to come over.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VII, 235; Bigelow, III, 188; Smyth, IV, 150).
  - to ----- -----., [1762. November ?]; A. Dr. of L.S. (First part of the letter missing.) 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    The hill-side [of Madeira] affords all climates; they claim 90,000 inhabitants; cultivation of wheat and corn increases and that of the vine diminishes, because of the greater and more speedy profits from the former. Concerning Dr. Barker who used to talk of lands he had in America. Remembrances to the Speaker [Mr. Isaac Norris] and his brothers, and to Mr. [John] Blackburn and Mr. Cooper.
  - to [Caleb] Whitefoord., 1762 December 7; A. Dr. of L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Thanks him for congratulating him on his son's appointment as Governor of New Jersey. The taking of Havana. Painting and poetry in America; his British lyre.
    Printed in Works (sparks, VII, 242; Bigelow, III, 215; Smyth, IV, 183).
  - to Dr. [John Fothergill]., 1762 December 8; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Arrived in Philadelphia and had the happiness of finding his family well. The anatomical drawings and casts that he sent over arrived safely at the [Pennsylvania] Hospital except the breaking of some of the glasses which the Managers repaired.1 Congratulates him on the taking of Havana.
    1 See History of the Pennsylvania Hospital, by T.G. Morton, Phila., 1897, p. 356.
  - to [Edward] Nairne., 1762 December 8; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Requests to be informed whether he paid for the magnet. Asks him if he could make a thermometer according to the enclosed directions and to forward it to him. Mrs. [Margaret] Stevenson will pay for it; his respects to Mr. [John] Canton.
  - to Mrs. Deborah Franklin., 1762; A.L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Billy is down at Bath. Received a letter inviting him there, but must not leave London as he daily expects bills drawn on him by the Trustees. Shall be glad to receive an account of what is due on Mr. Spoffard's mortgage, as he hopes to recover it from the sellers who never acquainted him that such a mortgage subsisted, though they must have known it. Shall soon send some music for the harpsichord.
    (Upper half of sheet missing.)
  - to ------ -------., 1763 February 9; A. Dr. of L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    His expenses and compensations while in England as Agent for the Province of Pennsylvania. Difficulty of separating private from public expenses.
    Printed in Works (Bigelow, III, 229).
  - to Dr. [John] Pringle and Mr. [William] Strahan., 1763 February 22; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Thanks for congratulations on his son's promotion. Congratulates him on the glorious peace that has been concluded, and which is the most advantagenous to Great Britain of any that history recorded. As to the places left or restored to France he conceives that their strength will soon increase to such a degree in North America that in any future war they may reduce them all with ease and therefore looks upon them as so many hostages or pledges of good behavior from that perfidious Nation. Must soon make a journey to his country but is sorry he shall not be able to meet him; trusts they will meet in a better country with better constitutions and vigorous bealth and everlasting youth.
    P.S. Sends his best wishes to Miss Ludwell and the other ladies.
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin, Philadelphia., 1763 February 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Trenton N.J
    Dined at Bristol and got here last night. Sir John Sinclair obligingly offered his chariot and four for the rest of the journey.
  - to ----- -----., 1763 February 26; A. Dr. of L. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Perth Amboy
    Thanks him for his kind endeavors in obtaining the discharge of James Forrester. Condoles with him on the repeated grievous breaches that have been made in his family. It has been discovered that quick silver is a melted metal. Relative to the solidifying and melting of mercury. Relative to some experiments to procure cold by evaporation.
  - Statement of Accounts of James Franklin, Deceased, and Benjamin Franklin., 1763 April 4; A. Dr. of Mem S. B[enjamin] Franklin. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
  - to [Mrs. Deborah Franklin]., 1763 June 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. New York
    Purposes taking Sally [Franklin] with him; Mr. [James] Parker will go with her and take care of her, if there is no other suitable compay. Approves of her opening his English letters.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VII, 254; Bigelow, III, 240; Smyth, IV, 202).
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin, Philadelphia., 1763[?]. October 31; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. New York
    Purposes to proceed homeward the next day if the weather is suitable. Will make a stay at Woodbridge and then shall go forward to Burlington, where he would like to meet her if she can manage to come there; will be home Saturday if he does not meet her at Burlington.
  - to ------ -----., [1763 ?]; A. Dr. of L.S. B[enjamin] F[ranklin] and J[ohn] F[oxcroft]. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Will send the maps of America as soon as they return from their journey. Shall endeavor punctually to comply with every order and every intimation of the pleasure of the Postmaster General, and shall exert their utmost abilities to improve this part of the revenue. Several Governors of Provinces refused payment of postage, of which he acquainted the Board when he was in London, but some have since paid their account; have hopes of obtaining payment from the others.
    (First part of letter missing.)
  - to ----- -----., [1763.]; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Introducing Mr. [William?] Smith, a young man of liberal education and excellent character.
  - Table of Distances and Rates of Postage in North America., [1764.]; A. Dr. of Mem. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - to [George] Whitefield., 1764 June 19; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Confidence in divine goodness. Hopes that the bugbcar Boston account of the unhealthiness of Philadelphia will not deter him from visiting them.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VII, 261; Bigelow, III, 250; Smyth, IV, 248).
  - to ------ -----., 1764 September 21; A. Dr. of L.S. B[enjamin] F[ranklin] and J[ohn] F[oxcroft]. 10p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Received his letter and gave orders for the several Acts of Parliament referred to, to be observed and executed by the officers. Is greatly concerned that the state of their accounts are delayed so long. Cause of this delay. The rule for charging 2d. or 16 gr. of silver on every letter coming from a ship is observed here; think the office would lose if they charged but a penny a letter. Amendments which they propose for the security of correspondence as well as for the advantage of the revenue. Advise that charge for postage be made according to the number of miles letters are carried.
  - to The Freemen of Pennsylvania, 1764 September 28; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Relative to some amendments which the Governor proposed to a bill passed by the Assembly for the punishment of certain offences, which amendments the Assembly refused to admit. This is one of their offences against the Lord Proprictors for which they were abused with all the virulence that malice can dictate, enforced by numberless barefaced falschoods that only the most dishonest can and would dare to invent.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, IV, 94; Bigelow, III, 305; Smyth, IV, 261).
  - to [Colonel Henry Bouquet]., 1764 September 30; A. Dr. of L.S. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Thinks of [Col. John] Bradstreet's peace [with the western Indians] as he does. Requests that if he writes any letter relating to the present expedition, which is likely to be seen by the Secretary of State, that he will mention him as ever ready to promote the service of the Crown. Tells him that his sentiments of the Constritution are solid and just. Until the change now attempted is effected there will be little internal quiet in the administration of Public Affairs. Voltaire on the subject or religious toleration. Gives a passage which, now that we are torn to pieces by faction, religious and civil, shows that it is advantageous to us that he views us at a favorable distance. Quotation in French concerning unjust criminal laws; what should be accepted as proof or evidence; presumptions should be excluded. Sends a pamphlet entitled "Jugement rendu dans I'affaire du Canada". Thinks it may interest him as during his war with that Colony he must have known some of the characters concerned.
    printed in Works (Bigelow, X, 305; Smyth, IV, 267).
  - Remarks on the Late Protest Against the Appointment of Mr. Franklin as Agent for the Province of Pennsylvania, [1764.]; Diss. (Incomplete.) 6p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    [This manuscript was issued as a pamphlet, in Philadelphia in 1764.]
    Printed in Works (Sparks, IV, 143; Bigelow, III, 356; Smyth IV, 273).
  - Epitaph on Mr. [William] Hogarth, [1764 November.]; A.N. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - to Mrs, [Deborah] Franklin, Philadelphia. Isle of Wight., 1764 December 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Have this moment come to an anchor here. Had terrible weather. Their friends' kind prayer for a thirty-day wind was favorably heard.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VII, 281; Bigelow, III, 259; Smyth, IV, 288).
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin, Philadelphia., 1764 December 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Is recovering from a violent cold which lasted 10 or 12 days. Given a cordial welcome by his old friend in London. Parliament does not meet till the 10th of next month.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, IV, 288).
  - Schedule of Letters Received at the Post Office., A. Mem. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - Plan for the Settlement of the Westward., [1764.]; A. Dr. of Mem. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - Specifications for a New Dwelling House., [1764.]; A. Dr. of Mem. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - to Mrs. Deborah Franklin., 1765; A.L.S. 2P.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Domestic affairs, his house, etc.
  - Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin, Philadelphia., 1765 February 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    His health. Mrs. [Margaret] Stevenson bought the things she wrote for. Hopes to be able to return about the end of the summer. Will purchase a watch for Sally [Franklin]. News of Col. [Henry] Bouquet's success gave great satisfaction in London.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VII, 283; Bigelow, III, 370; Smyth, IV, 358).
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin, Philadelphia., 1765 February 14; A.L.S. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Sends her several articles. Glad their pamphlet gave her so little concern. Tells her to allow no one to make her uneasy with idle, malicious stories and scribblings. Hopes a few months will finish affairs in England and bring him to that retirement and repose with his family on which he has so long set his heart.